In 1898, Marie /mə'ri:/ and Pierre /pi'ɛə/ Curie /ˈkjʊəri/
discovered radium /ˈreɪdiəm/.
Claimed to have restorative /rɪˈstɔːrətɪv 滋补品；兴奋剂  / properties /ˈprɒpətɪ 特性/,
radium was added to toothpaste /ˈtuːθˌpeɪst 牙膏/,
medicine,
water,
and food.
A glowing /ɡləʊ （无火焰地）发光/, luminous /ˈluːmɪnəs 发光的/ green,
it was also used in beauty products
and jewelry.
It wasn't until the mid-20th century
we realized that radium's harmful
effects as a radioactive element /ˈelɪmənt/
outweighed /ˌaʊtˈweɪ 比…重要/ its visual benefits.
Unfortunately, radium isn't the only
pigment /ˈpɪɡmənt 颜料/ that historically /hɪˈstɒrɪkli/
seemed harmless or useful
but turned out to be deadly.
That lamentable /ˈlæməntəbəl 使人惋惜的/ distinction /dɪˈstɪŋkʃən 区分/ includes
a trio /ˈtriːəʊ 三件套/ of colors and pigments /ˈpɪɡmənt 颜料/
that we've long used to decorate ourselves
and the things we make:
white,
green,
and orange.
Our story begins with white.
As far back as the 4th century BCE,
the Ancient Greeks treated lead /li:d/ to make
the brilliant /ˈbrɪljənt 有才智的/ white pigment we know today.
The problem?
In humans, lead is directly absorbed /əbˈsɔːb/
into the body
and distributed /dɪˈstrɪbjuːt/ to the blood,
soft tissues,
and mineralized /'mɪnrəl,aɪz 使矿物化/ tissues.
Once in the nervous /ˈnɜːvəs/ system,
lead mimics /ˈmɪmɪk 模拟的/ and disrupts the normal
functions of calcium /ˈkælsɪəm/,
causing damages ranging
from learning disabilities
to high blood pressure.
Yet the practice  /ˈpɑːtɪkəl 微粒/
of using this toxic /ˈtɒksɪk/ pigment
continued across time and cultures.
Lead white was the only practical choice
for white oil or tempera /ˈtempərə 蛋彩画/ paint
until the 19th century /ˈsentʃəri/.
To make their paint, artists would grind /ɡraɪnd 磨碎/
a block of lead into powder,
exposing highly toxic dust particles /ˈpɑːtɪkəl 微粒/.
The pigment's liberal /ˈlɪbərəl 自由的/ use resulted
in what was known as painter's colic /ˈkɒlɪk 腹绞痛/,
or what we'd now call lead poisoning.
Artists who worked with lead complained
of palsys /ˈpɔːlzi 麻痹/,
melancholy /ˈmɛlənkəlɪ  忧郁/,
coughing /kɒf/,
enlarged /ɪnˈlɑːdʒ/ retinas /ˈrɛtɪnə 视网膜 /,
and even blindness.
But lead white's density /ˈdɛnsɪtɪ 密度/, opacity /əʊˈpæsɪtɪ 不透明/,
and warm tone /təʊn  色调/
were irresistible /ˌɪrɪˈzɪstɪbəl 无法抗拒的 / to artists like Vermeer,
and later, the Impressionists /ɪmˈpreʃənɪst/.
Its glow /ɡləʊ/ couldn't be matched,
and the pigment continued to be widely
used until it was banned in the 1970s.
As bad as all that sounds,
white's dangerous effects
pale /peɪl 苍白的/ in comparison /kəmˈpærɪsn/
to another,
more wide-spread pigment, green.
Two synthetic /sɪnˈθɛtɪk 合成/ greens called
Scheele's Green and Paris Green
were first introduced in the 18th century.
They were far more vibrant /ˈvaɪbrənt 充满生气的/ and flashy /ˈflæʃi 浮华的/
than the relatively /ˈrelətɪvli/ dull /dʌl 沉闷的/ greens
made from natural pigments,
so they quickly became popular choices
for paint
as well as dye /daɪ 染料/ for textiles /ˈtekstaɪl/,
wallpaper,
soaps /səʊp/,
cake decorations,
toys,
candy,
and clothing.
These green pigments were made from
a compound /ˈkɒmpaʊnd/ called
cupric /kju:prik 二价铜的/ hydrogen arsenic /ˈɑːsnɪk 砷 /.
In humans, exposure /ɪkˈspəʊʒə 暴露/ to arsenic /ˈɑːsnɪk 砷 /
can damage the way cells
communicate and function.
And high levels of arsenic /ˈɑːsnɪk 砷 / have been
directly linked
to cancer and heart disease.
As a result, 18th century fabric
factory workers were often poisoned,
and women in green dresses
reportedly collapsed /kəˈlæps/
from exposure to arsenic on their skin.
Bed bugs were rumored not to live
in green rooms,
and it's even been speculated /ˈspɛkjʊˌleɪt 猜测/ that
Napoleon /pəuliən/ died from slow arsenic poisoning
from sleeping in his green
wallpapered bedroom.
The intense toxicity /tɒkˈsɪsəti 毒性/ of these green
stayed under wraps /ræp/
until the arsenic recipe /ˈrɛsɪpɪ/ was published
in 1822.
And a century later, it was repurposed
as an insecticide /ɪnˈsɛktɪˌsaɪd 杀虫剂/.
Synthetic /sɪnˈθetɪk 合成的/ green was probably the most
dangerous color in widespread use,
but at least it didn't share radium's
property of radioactivity /ˌreɪdiəʊækˈtɪvəti 放射性/.
Another color did, though - orange.
Before World War II, it was common /ˈkɒmən/
for manufacturers of ceramic /səˈræmɪk 陶瓷的/ dinnerware
to use uranium /juˈreɪniəm/ oxide /ˈɒksaɪd 氧化物/ in colored glazes /ɡleɪz 釉/.
The compound produced brilliant
reds and oranges,
which were appealing attributes,
if not for the radiation they emitted /ɪˈmɪt 散发/.
Of course, radiation was something
we were unaware /ˌʌnəˈweə 不知不觉地/ of until the late 1800s,
let alone /əˈləʊn/ the associated cancer risks,
which we discovered much later.
During World War II,
the U.S. government confiscated /ˈkɒnfɪˌskeɪt 没收/ all uranium
for use in bomb development.
However, the atomic /əˈtɒmɪk/ energy commission
relaxed /rɪˈlækst/ these restrictions in 1959,
and depleted /dɪˈpliːt 耗尽/ uranium returned to ceramics /sɪˈræmɪk 陶瓷制品/
and glass factory floors.
Orange dishes made during
the next decade
may still have some hazardous /ˈhæzədəs 有危险的/ qualities
on their surfaces to this day.
Most notably /显著地/, vintage /ˈvɪntɪdʒ 葡萄酒/ fiestaware /fiˈestə 节日/
reads positive for radioactivity.
And while the levels are low enough that
they don't officially pose a health risk
if they're on a shelf,
the U.S. EPA warns against eating food
off of them.
Though we still occasionally run
into issues with synthetic /sɪnˈθetɪk 合成的/ food dyes /daɪ 染料/,
our scientific understanding has helped us
prune /pruːn 修剪 删除/ hazardous /ˈhæzədəs 有危险的/ colors out of our lives.